hello it's July 1st 2023 we're in
physics as information processing in the
second discussion so thanks all for
joining and we'll see who else comes in
if you're watching live feel free to
write questions in the live chat and
I'll relay them onwards so Andre thanks
and uh it would be awesome to begin with
a little bit of some overview and some
points that you wanted to get to
yeah thank you Daniel
um so good morning everyone so if you
would start
up a bit
goal with Chris
last time
so I have a few slides that I singled
out
so now we're getting to
uh reform reformulation of quantum
theory in terms of reformulation
so
opposed to the dynamical theory
and uh as we've talked in previous
sessions we need to
a little bit philosophically uh with the
ontology of measurement entails
um so Chris last lecture started with
these three basic ingredients
so an action
that's
um number one a thing to ask you about
uh this is the qubit the physical
degrees of freedom that we need to
perturb in some way to ask a question
and then finally mathematics a language
that makes sense a context that makes
sense of of that information that we got
so
um
I should say number one
that came up in the first fashion when
um I can't I can't exactly remember but
at some point we talked about what is
information and we came up with uh
or we brought up a definition that goes
something like this it's the nicer Dash
it's uh differences that make a
difference this is
um Chris told me I can remember who who
first coined this Dash but I think it
it's quite old at least
early early 70s anyway so number one
basically let's curve that part right if
I want to gather some information I need
to perturb a system somehow so I need to
act and this is in early in in units of
actions right so units of energy times
time and we provided the example of
productsing right which is
apparently near optimal from the quantum
perspective this is mechanically what
goes on in your eyes and slide comes in
and this is clearly the difference that
makes a difference in your in your brain
the second part were the physical
degrees of freedom so recall that
um
we had a boundary okay so this this
theory of of quantum mechanics as
measurement necessarily breaks down the
system into a bipartite system with a
boundary and
you are
which are a lot smaller than um then the
degrees of freedom of A and B
uh at least in terms of the dimension of
the Hilbert space
and
um
change all right
sorry can you repeat Andre
I repeat what sorry just last 30 seconds
yeah so so the second ingredient is
it the the physical medium in which this
information exchange occurs
um
where the physical decrease of Freedom
the qubitsar
um arranged and these are physically
perturbed in order to mediate that
difference that makes a difference
so we can think of this dually as either
preparing those qubits or decoding those
qubits
and then finally there was the notion of
um
the reference frame
okay
so this Theory necessitates
a free choice of the agent of a
reference frame and physically what this
amounts to is three choice of
uh a measurement axis for those for
those uh qubits so we can think of
measuring disease being
uh in those periods on the binary so you
know that that requires a free choice of
of that axis
and this you know amounts to your
reference frame the context in which
those measurements are are performed on
one
extreme case we have that if if those
references are perfectly aligned
then the exchange of information is is
noiseless uh there was it somewhere over
here I think
I can't quite recall but generically
this these two reference frames of Alice
and Bob A and B are not exactly the same
they get to they get to choose the
reference frames I think it's all the
way
on the bottom actually right
so they can be aligned if they're
aligned they are exchanging noiseless
information right there is no
Randomness if they are not
superposition
and that's when you're gonna get you
know probabilities in in the outcomes
trivial probabilities
so parts are good
yes okay
so I have a few more comments of the
main things okay I'll take me just a few
minutes and then we can chat back and
forth
perhaps this slide is
interesting important I remember this is
where I asked the question myself
because I was I mean I still you know
it's it's not easy to wrap your hair
around what's going on here so we said
that measurement and preparation are
completely dual pictures
so this is going to be expanded on in
the next lecture
but
a jerk uh corollary of that is that
if you prepare crystal in similar terms
if you prepare something in a certain
State and then you
uh measure it right away you should
expect that it's still in that state
right so uh intuitively speaking this
induces the cycle right and uh where you
have preparation and measurement and you
you're back to square one so to speak
yeah and uh
in in in in generating that cycle
obviously there has to be some notion of
time right
so
um that's that's where
we're gonna have to make sense of uh the
distinction between internal and
external time if we take this
measurement operator and here perform
some operations
we can write it as a unitary propagator
from quantum mechanics which again
preserves information it just leaves the
state as it is
but with this little trick of the weak
rotation you can write it as e to the
measurement up to a constant and that
you know precisely encodes
at least morally speaking uh what we
just said right that this preparation
measurement thing is a cycle and more
importantly it gets rid of this T
external time
and
presumably
in in here it's going to be replaced by
some notion of internal time we're going
to have an internal time qrf
that is quote unquote the true
local time as the Observer proceeds
um I'm
not entirely certain of the details but
now looking at it here the beta which
uh presumably there's a you know the
beta and inverse temperature here
um I think this is going to be
intimately related to Notions of thermal
time this has been explored in papers by
rovelli
um called you know internal tanker revs
and thermal time is the way in which the
Observer observes the passage of time
uh those papers of royalty are linked in
the Q a by the way so I can also provide
links later
uh I think there might have been a
question should I stop yeah Dean go for
it and there's I was curious about this
because what I heard Chris start this
session with was that he
was going to try to help us understand
when we are looking at something through
a mechanical lens
so quantum mechanics and to me this
slide was the way of addressing as he
said his words were characterized
information transfer in a Quantum
theoretic way that the that the
translation from H to m
took the the mechanics aspect out of the
change or timepiece it was the
purification the most theoretical form
of transfer of information as opposed to
pulling up just the one ordered or
sequenced or mechanical lens
did I I heard you asked the question and
I kind of smiled because I thought to
myself no I understand why Anders is
asking this question it's can something
be both gripper in this in the
conceptual meaning sense ontologically
and gripped a physical object and I
think what that I thought maybe I was
misintermining I'd like your what your
perspective on this is that ability to
go from H to m
is what allows us to have both the
mechanical
and the theoretical the transference in
its purest sense is that being able to
have both
both can be true is that what it is
yes for sure yeah
yeah
um yeah I I
much else uh to say here it's
it is it is true that um you can think
of the information transfer picture as
an enlargement or an addition to the
mechanical picture
and that I don't think that the
mechanical picture has to be just
you know thrown out completely I think I
think it's interesting to keep it to see
how it can be recovered from the
information uh
processing picture this reminds me
actually there is
um
an Italian physicist I think his name is
curry Bella and Dean if you want I can I
can link you the papers later who is
very fond of the information theoretical
approach to quantum mechanics and
deducing quantum mechanics from first
principles
and here is a paper
I think the title is physics without
physics or something like that where you
know he he treats
um uh this whole thing as a seller baby
seller automaton and
by taking the appropriate
scaling limits he derives
qft
now I'm interacting qfd so he says okay
let me start with some axioms how
information should be information
processing
I mean I'm doing very loose here then
get a cellular automaton out of this
and the tech scale and a record UFT
non-interacting qft at least
so you know start with a few axioms our
information processing recovery
mechanics from that
does that add to your question a little
bit
yeah so so all I want
all I'm trying to do is tie this back
into some of the live streams that we've
done in the past and I know I use
different language I I am not
a scientist and I've not studied Quantum
other than sort of in passing ways but I
do think that
what this spoke to me about was
something that I've always
tried to include which is that there's
the figure it out piece which to me is
the conceptual and the meaning part that
Chris talked about very clearly here and
then there's the outing of the figure
there's this sort of physical Edge and
Boundary that if you don't have an
awareness of both things happening
concurrently the preparation and the
measure
are a unitary absorb minimum of two
State then all bets are up in terms of
being able to
think of these these
propagators and operators and all of the
ways that we're trying to explain the
situation they're off so we have to have
both
we have to have that sense that there is
a transfer
but there are and there is the mechanics
we we have to keep both juggling all the
time so that's where I that's where this
one particular slide
was really quite uh both biased
confirming for me but I think it also as
you say is going to open up a lot that
July um yeah I agree I think this might
be the most you know important or
mysterious if you wish in his life
yeah and it turns the pyramid the
conventional approach here's the pyramid
into a top that can be spun
essentially with a rick rotation and it
and it validates how information
transfer probably gets short shrift in
most of this Quantum conversation but
it's it's probably at least an equal to
to the mechanical part the what what
order are we delivering this information
in
at that point I'll stop thanks yeah
foreign
thanks
um Alexi
hi can you hear me yep
uh so uh I mean I I'm an you know
um my mathematics teacher in high school
used to say this is beautiful but I
don't quite understand it so I I wanted
to maybe I have two questions but I'll
start with with this simpler one so when
Chris talked about the reference frame
uh and said common language you know I
think in Shannon common language is the
alphabet there's a receiver and Sandra
and in the alphabet that they share and
then Chris said this reference frame is
a physical thing like neurons or hands
or mouth and then I got lost because you
know if uh when I encode I modify
something in the on the hard drive then
the physical components of the hard
drive is the reference uh frame but
you know this is not the shared language
then you know so
that's my first question maybe I'll stop
here to to Really I understand we're
dealing in metaphors but I want to
understand that you know the reference
frame up or down if Bob and Alice
understand it similarly then is that
really physical I think
answer is that
increase would you give a better answer
start from beginning
is that both are
true at the same time I think Chris
would give you a better answer but
the
the semantics or the sorry the Sherling
which reference frame has to have a
physical embodiment
and and that's uh Hardware a piece of
Hardware it's it's a neuron or something
um in this case it's the your free
choice of the spin axis
and that that's your reference frame but
at the same time it's it's a physical
it's a physical piece of Hardware so
reference frames are both
a piece of Hardware but also a piece of
semantics
so if I take it from the language I
don't quite understand to computer
science so if Alice and Bob communicate
through a piece of memory whether it's
random access memory hard drive then
endless encode something on that hard
drive and Bob reads from the hard drive
so in that sense they understand how to
encode and decode but they use the same
physical piece that's the reference
frame would that be correct
I might just add one again
continuing with the computer science
let's just and and the Shannon alphabet
let's just say that these are plain text
character encodings
and so they share the same set of
character a through z encodings
that that is reflected somewhere
physically
and so if um if a message was if if a
message were sent
um from another letter it wouldn't
render properly it's like outside uh
they couldn't differentiate
um Omega from Zeta because they only
have the A through Z software pack
and so there's an informational
distinguishment that's facilitated by
the information that's classically
inscribed on the screen the memory
and there is is an embodied physical as
well as a semantic aspect
to that situation
all right I think I'm getting closer to
understanding so to move away from
computer science if Ellis is a painter
she took a brush dipped it in red paint
and painted on the canvas red and Bob
has the same understanding of red as
Ellis and then he looked at the canvas
in red red that it is both the physical
you know a mark on the canvas and and
the symbol of red right
yes and if if somebody had red green
color blindness the physical apparatus
was not able to to informationally
distinguish then right they they
couldn't make this Wick rotation into
the quantum cognitive space they
wouldn't be able to to um detect that
there was a red figure painted on a
green background
yeah okay
the key component here is that the the
reference frame is inside of the agent
it's you know if you're a color blind
there is something physical inside of
your head or your eyes or whatever
that does not allow you to see the
difference
so
so your semantics are affected
ultimately by
a physical piece of Hardware
well yeah maybe I used a bad example
because color actually is computed in
the brain and color blindness is not
necessarily physical so uh okay but I I
think I get it closer but you know if we
if I may ask another question I get lost
with a saying that preparation and
measurement are
they have to happen both and that when
you prepare when you read you modify so
I am okay with the act of writing the
act of encoding so when I encode
something such as I you know Mark red on
the canvas or I write to the hard drive
a I modify the hard drive that is true
but if I if I am asking a question right
I'm not modifying anything on the canvas
so in what way the act of asking the
question or Preparation is modifying the
qubit this is where I'm lost you know if
I does that make sense yeah I think this
is exactly a question I asked to
Christian in the Stream So
I can't quite remember his answer but I
think it was basically that they're
completely dual pictures
um in the sense of you know they're
they're both two ways of looking at the
same thing uh it was kind of like you
know evolving time
towards the future or or the past if you
have time symmetry you know you can you
can divide
um yeah so I I myself am slightly
confused by the very
but I think the answer is that they are
painting at the same
picture of or am I preparing are just
completely do okay that's I think well
do you remember that Daniel
yeah okay I'll give a different angle
than the um the formal Duality
relationship so let's think about our
measuring device is going to be a carpet
and we're interested in whether somebody
has walked on the carpet so to prepare
the carpet we comb it very nicely in One
Direction and I'm sure there's analogies
there with the um preparation of qubits
in a quantum computer but we're going to
comb the carpet
as an act of preparation
and then
something is going to happen maybe it's
a split second later and so we're very
confident that it should be still nicely
combed or maybe it's going to be a whole
working day later
but now we're going to take that probe
the tip whatever it may be and we're
going to run it along the carpet
and we're going to measure the state of
of the direction of the fibers of the
carpet
so if we didn't prepare the measurements
we wouldn't have a calibrated reference
point
to know how things had even changed
and so there's there's a cycle of
preparing the apparatus through
something like a calibration or at least
like a emptying of memory
to be able to then make an observation
and to have that observation have the
kind of meaning that we would have
expected like
Purge the photo detector make the
measurement now you have to purge it
again that's the preparation what do you
think Alexi
that is a beautiful metaphor and I dig
that except I think I heard Chris say
that when you prepare you make Cube it
into up or down and this is when I'm
lost because when you comb the carpet
you don't do that you don't put the
footstep on it in fact there may not be
any footstep right and this is this is
where I'm missing you know I think in
quantum physics as well if you measure
there's the cause and effect
relationships are broken here for me you
know if in my Act of preparation I'm
opening my canvas to to read the message
but I do not know what the message will
be I'm game but if he's saying that when
I prepare I modify the carpet such that
it becomes either up or down actually
not blank but up or down then I'm lost
you have to comb the carpet up or down
there's no blank carpet so you you um
you know you have a slate you have an
Etch A Sketch you could either make all
the pixels white and then you'd be able
to measure a message in the dark or you
can make all the message dark or the
Slate dark and then you could be able to
measure something that was light but you
pick a direction of polarization in your
preparation or calibration step so that
deviations from that can be the
measurements
so you're saying carpet is binary carpet
doesn't have multiple States carpet can
only have two states so if I prepare it
I effectively put it in one of those
States
well if they do anything yeah let's say
we had the carpet at a um 45 degree
angle mathematically we could describe
that as a mixed state
and it may not be the most effective
for measuring the movement of people
across the carpet but yeah you could
um Define it
um or comb it that way it doesn't
necessarily if it were only a binary it
wouldn't be a qubit then it would be a
classical bit
I actually
yeah with the with you know I I
you know recall lecture a couple of
slides more shoots
we briefly talked about it like 10
minutes ago
by preparing you are choosing an axis
and whatever you
up or down in that axis now that doesn't
mean that the environment gets to do its
own thing right
uh and he
superposition of uh outcomes but at
least you're measuring that axis
right so it's going to be either up or
down in that act
you can call it two pictures and
I have uh I just want to see a few words
on
graphic screens and Define my diagrams
and maybe
clarify question a little more
Dean
on this really really interesting I I
don't know how metaphorically you could
explain the carpet as a wave
but I think once you get away from the
it's up or down
that possibility enters the conversation
and the only reason I I
wonder whether or not metaphorically the
wave aspect of that can be included in
how you're describing the carpet is that
Chris spent quite a bit of time on the
all possible paths argument and in
particular and I love this when Alice
isn't looking
right well in that in that wave equation
how could Alice not be looking
that's what gets real I mean Alice could
not be looking if it's if it's binary if
it's or up or down
but if it's wave
it's on a it's on a
it's a unitary propagator I'm not sure
how
she takes her eyes off of this
preparation measure
thing that's going off all the time so
this is
this is actually an what I consider to
be a feature or an opportunity or an
opening in the sense that from a
strictly information transfer piece not
a mechanical piece now not a physical
thing
from an information transfer piece maybe
the carpet can be metaphorically
understood as a wave
that the eyes
of Alice or whoever's doing the
preparing and the measuring Bob Alice I
don't care peaches
that there is actually a difference then
between something that is exchanged
and something that is informationally
transferred
and again I don't think that the four of
us here sitting right now are going to
resolve that
but I wonder
If part of our
part of the difficulty in this is
finding the physical metaphor
that explains the
theoretical transfer in such a way that
it doesn't
it it breaks the Symmetry and
holds it because again we're back to
gripper and grip we're back to figuring
it out and Outing the physical figures
in the state that we're in and we have
to do both at once so
again Daniel you're you're the creative
guy how do you turn your carpet metaphor
into a wave equation
maybe there's a subwoofer in the room or
maybe somebody is um waving the carpet
but what what you what you said about
the um what is exchanged and what is
transferred
um maybe the transfer is the classical
component
uh um oh I I don't know which one will
be exchange or transfer but one of them
is the classical inscription that's how
many gigabytes were written or read to
the hard drive but what's exchanged
let's just say are the the semantics of
meaning
and given an appropriate co-preparation
maybe only one bit needs to be
transferred
for the exchange of a message that was
already triggered to be set off and then
also this entire discussion it it kind
of strikes me as like the uh
Cartesian duality of our time but rather
than mind and body it's the physicality
of information syntax
and the metaphysicality of information
semantics
and that's these kind of Two Worlds with
their own physics and metaphysics
that we're trying to connect
and it's like
similarly well is the information how
does the information world cause
something physical
how does the physical cause something
informational and I think that the
entire Journey that the course and
everyone is on is uh physics as
information processing that those as a
qualified and distinguished but minimum
of two set Alexi
yeah thank you so much uh can you hear
me yeah
I I I'm yeah Thinking Out Loud maybe but
I I think the way to get closer to
understanding in my head is to let go of
the metaphor of asking a question right
so if Alexis is talking to Daniel
through zoom and I pose even a closed
question up or down
so I you know uh formulated the question
and you know uh released it into Zoom
space and then I'm silent and I opened
my listening to your answer but you
Daniel have agency to stay up or down I
did not I do not have any effect on
whether you will say up or down right
and that's the difference so me asking
you a question does not modify uh the
answer you you decide Ellis talking to
Bob Bob has the agency to answer the
question not Alice and that that's where
I'm stuck so I don't know if asking a
question continues to be a good metaphor
preparing preparing the instrument for
measurement is is maybe better and and
so but but actually Alice is not asking
Bob Ellis is acting on a qubit
right and qubit is is a simple thing
that you know can can literally
physically be up or down I guess and so
that's that's maybe maybe that's the
answer that Ellis does not ask involved
Ellis does something to the qubit
and because qubit can be up or down then
that's no longer asking a question
asking a question implies your your
correspondent can can can tell you
anything
when we're dealing with the very
sophisticated process of natural
language question asking I think we're
dealing we're dealing with something
that that's orders
um of composition above the Kinder the
kind of binary ask so I I agree with
that
um it's almost like
um Alice prepares the photoreceptor so
it's slate is refreshed
and then it's the photon or the light
emitting object that has the agency to
send the photon or not I mean maybe the
measure the preparation occurs
and then no one comes back to check
whether or not agency was even exerted
and I think when we really focus on like
the Nano probe like Atomic Force
microscopy really tracing with a super
fine tip over the surface of something
or scattering x-rays when we really
think about the the
um moment
of information transfer we've realized
like
nothing comes for free and I think that
this question asking framework other
than really conveniently reads arrive in
quantum mechanics in one hour incredibly
helps us understand that we don't get to
ask it for free in terms of time we
don't get to ask it for free in terms of
energy and we don't get to ask free
floating questions with a question and
or agentic responder
are not involved already in a semantics
so I think it's calling attention to
um the components of an experiment or a
question or an opening
but agree that it's not always as simple
as a binary question but in the special
simple bazel case
it does
start there
you want to look at any of the um the
participant submitted questions if there
was any that struck your face let me
finish real quick I have like yeah maybe
five minutes to wrap this up uh so and
and this I think is going to at least in
part answer one of Dean's concerns so
the next thing we should uh very briefly
cover so let's talk a little bit about
you know holographic screens and also
uh this is the paper on the physical
media photographic principle so let's
take a look at also this picture
from that paper
this is the holographic boundary and you
know
nine hours principle and all these
thermodynamic constraints on information
processing
necessitate uh the breakdown of this
boundary in terms of you know free
energy extraction sectors memory sectors
and so on and by the way if you if you
read um the paragraphs around this
picture there's more details on how the
time qrf is is induced but we'll leave
that as it is for now uh
Dean what I meant by this answering your
your concern your concern was that you
don't see how Alice can take off her
eyes from the picture yeah uh but that's
precisely what's going on here right
there's there's a sector that's being
observed which is a subset of these
keywords
that are being observed but presumably
she has the freedom to you know say hey
this sector now I I declare as my
observation sector please I declare as
my memory sector this I declare us at my
through my uh free energy extraction
sector
so it is because of this fundamental
limits
on the amount of information processing
it is not true that she can she doesn't
have a an unidealized you know
you know laplacian if you wish
um access to all the degrees of freedom
she can only observe finally
uh a final amount of stuff so so she she
is forced to take her eyes off at least
part of the system at least for a while
right because otherwise you know all
this energy and time constraints that
Daniel was just mentioning you know
they're not we you have to abide by
those
so
um so a few things that Chris mentioned
in the last lecture when it came to this
holographic screen is well number one uh
we've got all the information exchange
is mediated by bits
uh here at the qubit at this holographic
screen
this in turn enforces
um a finiteness in the information
transfer if you wish there is not
infinitely uh an infinite amount of
information in finite space even if you
were to pack it at planckian density
which is presumably the limit that black
holes achieve it's still a finite amount
of information in a finite amount of
so if you have Finance you are taking
uh the other
is the following
um and again uh Chris will deal with
this at greater detail in perhaps
lecture five I think maybe four but it's
the notion of emergence base time which
is that a and b separately so you think
of you know these are presumably the
internal degrees of freedom what's going
on inside of a Alice at an abstract
level there may not be a notion of the
space
but you know
notion of space emerges at the boundary
and uh that's uh not easy to explain I
think
presumably has to do with
and stuff like
um and I don't know the full details
myself but but for now that's that's one
of the key things that that Chris
mentioned which is that an agent you
know may not have
a space but he may emerge honorary
okay
and
the last thing and I'm glad that to see
that this was mentioned already so it
saves us time I don't have to say it
again take us a minute
this
five months at least you can answer if
you're can you just turn off your video
under just so you don't have lag
yeah one second
yes
this notion of uh refinement diagrams
right
so
what is this whole thing about unitary
Evolution or preparation
the the scattering picture as Alice
preparing at the director of her
boundary right and writing it into her
memory
and then
measuring it at some point in future
right requires that you consider the
possible that happened to that
preparation okay so if there's
some amount of time passes
you're prepared you know your data time
T you look at it again at time t plus DT
you have to take into account all the
possible histories
it's just saying I prepared it here now
it's up to B what happens until the next
time I look at it
up to the environment so I I have to in
in that unitary Evolution I consider all
the possibilities right and that's
that's exactly you know the requirement
so let's just look at the computer
leave it there for now no we can open up
the discussion
so there's two things that are now where
was this yeah
yes
so uh-huh go ahead yeah so all I was
I'll I understand or I think I
understand
I think I understand that if I'm looking
at on or if I'm attending to on
I'm not looking it off
what what I saw in that wave thing with
vitamin was I could also be
looking at the switch
where the two different places of on and
off exist and when I'm looking at the
entire switch I'm not looking at one or
the other I'm looking at the
at that basal as Daniel described that
basal opportunity of both and and I
think that on that I don't know how that
ties in with reference frames but on
that level that says
I'm now
looking at all possible
in that moment I don't think at least
from that perspective that reference
frame I'm zooming into a on or off
binary Choice decision Branch I'm I'm
still at that place where the
preparation allows for for both I'm not
I'm literally not taking my eyes off at
that place so again I'm not arguing with
you because I what you describe and then
and the image that you brought up
all that is is bringing it down to a
granular level and saying if I'm paying
attention to this I can't be paying
attention to that but if I
physically
from a transfer perspective back up so
that I can see both both possibilities
at once I don't know that I'm taking my
eye off of either that's that's the only
thing that I was bringing up now of
course Chris will probably hear this and
go
Dean you got to go and rethink this
whole thing through which is great
because I'm here to learn but that's
again if I if I miss
if I miss
spoke about what I was trying to say it
wasn't because I
I don't see those moments when
I'm I'm directing my my preparation over
here and that's going to give me one
kind of measurement versus if I'm taking
in
a larger time frame and now or larger
spatial frame or larger holographic
screen like I don't even know how to
describe it because I just don't have
the words for it yet but
there you go I just want to be clear
that I'm not I don't think I'm confused
I just want to know the difference
between when I'm looking at on or off
and when I'm looking at the entire
switch that's all
I'll add one point on this slide
it goes back to some of the earliest
points that Chris made about the
ontological Primacy of communication
space and time arise from communicating
agents
communicating agents are not something
that we have to squeeze into an a priori
spatial Temple framework
so quantum mechanics saying here on the
slide is about measurement not
mechanical motion
so we don't need to wait around or
speculate as to how from the quote
mechanical or physical hard drive
measurement arises or happens
we start with the measurements occurring
and then different kinds of
sophisticated agents can conceptualize
of movements through spaces and times
and this also relates to Bayesian
mechanics as a mechanics and a physics
of movement on information geometric
spaces
and so
the physics can be projected by
appropriately prepared agents but we
don't necessarily need to wonder about
how that agent fits within a mechanical
setting and I guess this is where humans
are
with the I am a strange Loop girdle
Escher Bach gripper and gripped mystery
of being able to to see it multiple ways
Audrey do you want to go to the um
questions
yeah let me just say using remarks here
I think what Chris is uh
punch in line
of the paper uh free energy principle
for Quantum systems
which is you know morally speaking it's
similar to relative relaxation to
thermodynamical equilibrium which is
that if you have an isolated bipartite
Quantum system A and B are gonna turn
um are going to tend towards reference
Frame Alignment under for entanglement
and this these two things are
are basically very intimately related by
aligning the reference frames you'll get
a and b
will be driven towards maximal
entanglement
so uh should I
uh take a look at the questions and
okay
open this yeah
so so uh
if you guys have access to the Q a
ah there's been many more questions in
the last
you know bringing you guys attention to
a few of them uh this is where
um
Chris links uh to the papers of rubelli
which I mentioned earlier in passing
when we were talking about the
preparation measurement cycle and the
notion of thermal time or uh you know
subjective time if you wish
somebody Brew out this remark that you
know performing some calculations here
you can relate
T time to a change in
um
okay
a change in the volume of phase space or
you know more precisely the the amount
of available states in the state space
you know with a log and whatever uh with
respect to the energy right
and you know
so so this you know restates the
the idea that we're talking about
earlier right like your intrinsic uh
subjective time being
basically speaking that is uh Observer
dependent
so that's a a good question to
uh take a look at
um
there's another one what is what is
meant by local free of choice
uh this is a very good answer too local
here means that some boundary right
isolated uh systems are idealized by you
know definition there's always going to
be an observer interacting with an
environment so a nice purely isolated
system is an idealization so a local
free choice means here is exactly what
we said earlier right that you get to
choose the spin access at the boundary
qubits
um
I mean there were some nice questions
relating
Mark of blankets to the scattering
picture
uh so this one for instance it's also
worth a look
so somebody you know brought up this you
know
very good point about
the scattering Matrix the scattering
Matrix is by the way
you know let's not think about it
mathematically just uh
let's think about the picture right you
you imagine two particles that are
interacting
far away
they are free right they are specially
separated on interacting free particles
yeah and somehow at some point they come
to interact right and then you have to
write all the final diagrams for all the
exchange of bosons or whatever the
interaction is and and that's how you
would compute the amplitudes for the
scattering process right how those two
particles that were
you know separated came to interact
and then they go off to Infinity again
uh Chris here brings up the point that
in a sense how you define a mark of
blanket is you know in the opposite
direction right
you see micro blanket in at least in the
graph Theory sense you start with a node
and micro blanket is just the set of
nodes that
separate
in terms of conditional probability that
node from everyone else right and then
you can have edges which are going to be
directly uh causal networks so as you
click no no Cycles directed edges that's
that's how the graph looks
and you you build up so essentially
you're taking the opposite
um picture right you start with a node
which in this case would be the
interaction and then you build up to
Infinity
as opposed to in the scattering picture
which is like you start with
particles non-interacting at Infinity
let me see how they go off to Infinity
again and then the interaction is is in
the middle
uh So that obviously the answer is is a
bit more uh precise but it's it's worth
taking a look at
and
this is it an interesting one too
of a symmetrical input output y
bandwidth so again if you think of it as
a graph nothing is constraining you to
say that you're going to have more
incoming errors than outcoming errors
into the boundary right
that that's just the way it is you know
if you think of it a graph there is no
symmetry imposed the only natural sense
of symmetry would be energy conservation
and that's exactly what you know Chris
says here right which is that
um
and I'm not sure myself how you relate
it to
a conservation of not quite information
but you know
I I wouldn't know how to fix it myself I
would just take a look at the question
but basically you know there's a
priority nothing that necessitates
symmetry in input output in Market
blankets
but if you are to talk about any sort of
symmetry the natural language would not
be in terms of incoming versus outcome
in errors but rather
energy conservation which we we saw is
is you know a closed cost enough
information transfer right because of
the minimal requirements for Action to
rewrite a qubit
and the last question that I would like
to bring your you guys's attention to I
mean all of them are great
uh but we have finite resources and
finite times
on internet uh
would be
would be uh this one okay and I'm not
gonna go into too much detail
but this is again about
the local
wait no one second
um
so turn on my camera by the way Daniel
go for it
and also people people can see all the
questions on the website
right and submit their own as well
yes for sure
uh so and now I lost track of the
question that I wanted to show you guys
I think it's this one over here yes uh
yes exactly this one so by the way all
of them are good even this one the
holographic principle doesn't make it
easier to compute any physics problems
well
please take a look at Chris's answer but
all I can say is that this ideas of
holography I'm not an expert I'm not a
condensed matter physicist but they're
they're used all over physics nowadays
not necessarily just in high energy uh I
know that condensed matter theorists use
them all the time so the answer to this
is an emphatic yes
the holographic at least adhcft is used
all over but again I'm not a physicist
myself
um
so this is the last question I want to
do
bring your attention to
and uh here Chris uh this this may be
the one worth taking a look at in terms
of uh in order to answer
all uh
you know the earlier speculations that
we had about time
internal clock here somebody asks about
um
synchrony
and
you know just the perception of time
with respect to external clocks I
suppose
increase here answers that
at the end of the day any even if you're
using an external clock
everything that you perceive outside at
the end of the day has to be in terms of
an internal clock any information
incoming you're gonna have to you know
make causal sense of it you're gonna
have to write it into a memory in terms
of an internal clock so
so you're never going to be able to eat
this
so to speak increase your position of
the passage of time by taking an
external clock even if you think it's
more precise than anything you have
inside I think that's basically what his
answer amounts to and this is morally
related to you know all this Frame
halting problem stuff where because
I'm never as a system you're never going
to give an infinitely precise you know
I'm speaking very Loosely here an
infinitely precise description or
yourself you're you're never gonna
morally speaking again that's that's
what it amounts to you're never going to
be able to
outdo your internal clock by
by trying to leverage something external
like like you know an atomic clock that
even if you think it's more precise at
the end of the day
your own subjective
uh perception of information will depend
on internal clocks
so we can uh open up things and conclude
in remarks and
any other Alexi or Dean or anyone else
who may have joined
I don't have anything else to say at
this point
I mean where where or when are we we had
Session One
with a real big historical overview
section two we focused on
the measurability question
which is answered with a question and we
talked about some of the constraints
of question asking namely that it takes
time it takes energy you have to ask it
to somebody or something on an interface
and it has to have a semantic Quantum
reference frame
and this is
dovetailing with a free energy principle
of course because the free energy
Principle as it says in the syllables to
what does the free energy principle
apply and Chris says everything
measurable
that's why it's a theory of every thing
that we choose to measure model not
ontological statements about what is
and then where are we heading into in
session three
have you looked ahead under or do you
want me to read what's in the syllabus
uh please do yeah yeah I think basically
uh my short answer to that and possibly
my full answer also is that it's just
going to take care of the loose hands in
this lecture too so this lecture too is
a warm up to the to the real thing which
we need to talk more seriously about
reference friends to to in order to get
the precise
a picture of this Quantum measurement
process yeah yeah it says that session
three will introduce the idea of quantum
reference frames and the representation
using hierarchies of binary classifiers
these formal structures provide a
semantics for measurement and hence
provide the basis for a theory of
meaning for interacting agents the
language of qrfs allows a particularly
straightforward and intuitive definition
of variational free energy and so allows
a fully General Quantum formulation of
the fep we will see that the fpp is a
classical limit on the principle of
unitarity the fundamental principle of
quantum theory
okay
uh by the way uh Daniel can I I'm not
sure if you're busy but I just got an
email from Chris I think he may be
watching us
and I think he's just confused about the
link so Chris I don't know if you're
there still but
um
do you think it's worth it can we send
him the link real quick if you can come
for a few yeah
I'll I'll send Chris the um the zoom
link now so yeah
hold on to your qubit Chris we're coming
yeah
so let's let's give him a few minutes
maybe he's still watching and he'll
he'll answer the questions better than I
could well well Daniel is sending him
sending him a Lifeline can I
just from the from the the rookie
perspective on this
Session One seemed like there was a big
time window like the historical piece
over using an external clock and a
timeline this one felt like the parabola
and the up or down and the entanglement
was
almost instantaneous in terms of that
plank length that we were really holding
up as comparative to that timeline that
chronological timeline and so I'm
guessing that now that we've established
those two as different
where does that go but again that's just
the rookies view of things
hey Chris welcome
yeah hi this is a very interesting
discussion
um and it it's uh given me some pointers
as to what to emphasize
at the beginning of session three
uh but I I can say in response to Dean's
question
that the time when Alice isn't looking
is the time during which Bob is making
his measurement and then his next
preparation step
so if you if you consider again that
slide that shows uh
sort of the Feynman representation of
what's Happening
as this unitary flow
that's what Bob is doing and I think
Andrew said that
oh from Alice's point of view
Bob is just some Quantum system and
she's banged on that system by asking a
question
and now that system is doing something
or other that she can't see until it it
I.E Bob bangs on his side of the screen
and she gets some information by making
a measurement
oh so
she she may be not looking for a very
short period of time
oh right according to her internal clock
she's not looking for just the time it
takes for one of her internal ticks to
take place
but uh in in general
oh we're not saying anything about how
long that time is right if you think of
this in a scattering Theory way
oh then we're talking about the time
between two protons leaving the Rings
on the uh
Large Hadron Collider
to the time that all the stuff that
comes out of their Collision is measured
by the detectors
which is a nanosecond or something like
that some very short period of time
so just just think of that interval as
the
the measure of the intrinsic uh
time dependence external time dependence
of the interaction
someone has to do something and then
someone else has to do something and
there's a gap
between what the first person does and
what they see in response
oh let's see what's the other question
uh the the other central question that
came up today
was the question of why observing
something requires action
and of course in the in the classical
picture observing something doesn't
require any action at all
the the event just happens
and this is the the fundamental if you
will distinction between classical and
quantum theory
is that making an observation in in
quantitory is taking an action on the
world
and there's a lovely metaphor that's
that's not
correct in detail but it's it's very
useful I think conceptually
uh which Heisenberg came up with to try
to explain his uncertainty principle too
his classical colleagues
they said look suppose I'm trying to to
see a very small particle and measure
its motion
uh I have to have a microscope to see
this particle
and to measure its motion I need to to
light it up and shine some light on it
and those photons of light are actually
impacting the thing I'm trying to see
so the the act of observation itself
requires banging something into an
object uh
and uh when we're just looking out at
the world it's the sun that's banging
the light into the object not us
but we can we can sort of merge those
two systems together because it's the
sun that's taking the action
that lets us get some information
that the sun is perturbing the things
that we're looking at by banging photons
into them
um
and I think that that picture of of
Heisenberg's is what uh he used to to
actually derive the uncertainty
principle in terms of momentum and uh
position because banging something into
something is transferring momentum to it
photons transverse of momentum to the
tiny particle in the microscope
and that perturbs its position on the
microscope stage which is precisely what
Heisenberg is trying to measure so
that's his his point in that analogy
observation itself always takes action
and that's why observation and and
preparation are duels and quantum theory
because they each require a minimum one
unit of action and I think Andrew you
said the The Duality can be thought of
in terms of time and variance and that's
exactly correct
preparations just measurement run
backwards right and vice versa and if
you let me say a few words I think this
also answers my own confusion and the
one that Alexi the question that Alexi
post earlier
which is this Duality between
preparation and measurement in your
picture that you're bringing up Chris
with a Heisenberg by
shining photons on a particle that I'm
trying to observe
um these pictures of preparation and
measurement are dual because in in doing
so I'm constraining the system in trying
to measure it I'm constraining it so
it's so in in me trying to gather
information by shining photos on it what
I'm really doing is I'm constraining it
I'm just saying
you can only take this this you know
momenta or or position is is would that
be correct
of
yeah in fact your
in the microscope example it's
particularly clear you're you're
bouncing a photon off of the object and
then it's that Photon that you're
detecting
right oh there there was one other
question that uh can be answered quickly
it was the question about uh what's the
reference frame
yeah uh Alice is using when she's uh
measuring up or down measuring her spin
up or down
and of course they're they're several
reference frames involved here
uh so let's work inwards uh in a real
system Alice is sitting here she's got a
Stern gerlock apparatus which is a
vertical magnet apparatus
and she's measuring the spin of an
electron that's that's traveling through
this Stern gerlock device and what the
certain gurlock device does is is Orient
the spin uh with a magnetic field that's
that's not homogeneous so it ends up
pointing physically up
uh as it comes through the apparatus
so
how is that apparatus oriented I mean
what defines the up direction for that
apparatus
well in the Practical setting what
defines that
apparatus orientation is the Earth's
gravitational field right we're sitting
we're in we're here in the laboratory
and the Earth's gravitational field
tells us what direction is down it's
toward the center of the Earth
and so up is away from the center of the
earth and that's what defines the axis
for the apparatus which is a great big
piece of metal so it's very responsive
to the gravitational field
so now we can ask about Alice right
Alice is also embedded in this
gravitational field
and she also can detect the
gravitational field she can tell which
way is down toward the center of the
Earth
by the the force acting on her feet
and that measurement is taking place in
Alice's brain
so in Alice's brain there's a
representation of which way is up and
that's the internal reference frame of
Alice that lets her do the experiment
you know if she was freely floating in
space
but the apparatus was anchored to the
gravitational field
she wouldn't be able to tell that it was
anchored to the gravitational field
that's Einstein's the point that
Einstein makes in all of those
experiments where he has observers
flying around in spacecraft
uh that they have to have their own
reference frame
oh what what Einstein didn't emphasize
was that reference frame is in their
head it's encoded by their nervous
system
oh so uh I I think it was Daniel who
said this exactly correctly that uh the
physical object uh in her head that the
actual neural network that tells her
which way the gravitational field is
uh is itself a semantic object I mean
that's that's what
gives the word up and down meaning for
Alice and what is what is what do I mean
when I say the word meaning I mean it
lets her take some action
um
semantics boils down to actionability if
it gives things significance
and this this was the point that that
Bateson was making when he said
differences that make a difference
uh for a for an organism
something is Meaningful if it actually
makes a difference for what I can do
uh in this world that I'm trying to
survive in
oh so I'll I'll leave it at that but
this is this is very very useful for uh
leading off the next session so thank
you very much for for all of that
discussion
awesome thank you I guess if I could say
one thing here is that let me scroll
back up to the three points early in the
night
differences that make a difference
would tell you that you require action
to to perturb the system and measure and
then the semantics or the contextuality
that may be encoded in in the in the
nervous system would tell you what is
the difference that it's being made
would that be correct yeah
right what what tells you that there's a
difference there it's it's what what
you're able to detect and represent
internally
oh it's almost like step one do
differently step two you have to ask it
to a different thing and then three you
need the semantic frame that makes a and
b different
differences all the way down
um well we will
transcribe this and fix the few patchy
moments enter we'll work together on
updating the transcript so that
everybody who wants to be well prepared
for the measurement of the third lecture
will be absolutely in place
thank you Chris for joining that's a fun
fun cap to this discussion so all right
thank you see you all next time bye